There's a common misconception with the GPU scarcity problem, which is everyone thinks just we need more GPUs.
I need more bullets! That is pretty far from the truth.
We're the only ones in deep end or in crypto that are able to do that today.
There's no point in buying a ton of bullets if you don't have soldiers that know how to shoot or you don't have the right guns to use them.
Most Web3 companies don't want to show their revenue because if they did, everyone would realize that this project is grossly overhabited.
All these enterprise-grade compute providers, they work on very, very long-standing contracts.
There's difficulty. Different regions get different contracts at different times.
And so if you have a single aggregation layer, it makes it a lot cleaner and a lot simpler.
And then when you bring crypto economics, token economics to it, you're actually able to provide this at a significantly lower cost.
See, that's why I love to kill.
Let's say you have like a $50 chip. As long as it has access to the internet and has a screen, you can plug into the cloud and you can have an iPhone.
Can this underutilized compute actually do what the AI needs to do?
A lot of these deep end projects are still more affected by general crypto sentiment than it is by the AI sentiment.
We see crypto projects addressing this GPU scarcity problem by selling nodes.
It allows users to provide their own GPU compute power for these AI gaming movie companies to use.
A company would need GPUs that are operational 24-7.
When the GPUs are controlled by retail users, isn't it difficult to prevent issues like power cuts or shortages?
That is one of the reasons why Aether is probably the only deep end project that can truly actually service these enterprise grade customers.
Every single deep end project today does something very, very unique.
Obviously within deep end, we're all competing for mindshare and we're all competing for user recognition.
But what we do at a business level is very, very different.
Ionet acts as a very high level orchestration layer.
Render is very much so for consumer compute to plug in and do render jobs.
You have projects like Grass, which is using essentially your computer's bandwidth.
And for us, we're really, really focused on this enterprise grade gaming and AI use cases.
Very few companies in the world that can actually provide cloud gaming to hundreds of millions of users at the same time.
In Web2 or Web2, there's maybe a total of 10 to 20 companies that can do it.
In Web3, there's definitely only one. It's hard for any crypto company to say that they have guaranteed buying or guaranteed demand for the utility of the token.
So when I hear your revenue, I'm like, wow, that sounds like a lot.
But how does that number compare to other deep end projects?
It's not gonna sound great when I say it, but we have more monthly revenue than the lifetime revenue of all other deep end projects combined.
NVIDIA在過去這一年上漲了175%
台積電在過去這一年上漲了75%
衝破1000塊台幣的大關喔
Facebook, Dropbox, Whatsapp, Instagram, TikTok
這些很硬底子的公司
都花了好多年的時間才達到1億個用戶
OpenAI旗下的Chall GPT只花了2個月就達到了
這一種瘋狂的成長背後需要很大的這個計算能力跟GPU
那我們通常講到算力
我們直覺就會想到這些傳統的公司
但是加密貨幣呢
居然也有反映真實世界算力需求的項目喔
這一節很有意思
因為每一個币圈算力領域的項目呢
都想要把自己叫做币圈的NVIDIA 對吧
但是誰真的稱得起這個稱號呢
不讓你來評斷
überzeug Penn Penn Penn Penn
queen of the game. Stacking crypto like it's her claim to fame. If you want success, then take a
look away. Well, hi, Dayden. Hey, Vani. Well, thank you for being here. You are the Web3
Chief Architect of Aether. What is a Web3 Chief Architect? Essentially, what I oversee is a lot
of our native Web3 activity. That includes token swaps, staking, DeFi integrations, building out
more of the protocol as well. The Aether team has a very, very strong and extensive background in
cloud gaming, low latency inference, AI, building distributed GPU cloud. And I came on to add a
little bit more Web3 native flavor to the core team. That's essentially what I look at. Also
building out pieces for governance and foundation setup and things like that. So you are crypto
native? Yeah. So I've been in crypto, I think, almost five years now, closing in on the anniversary
since I first lost a ton of money buying Bitcoin. What were you doing before joining Aether then?
When I was in university, I had a very small startup in Singapore that was mainly doing
marketing and high quality video production for brands like Porsche, McLaren, Bensley,
long list of automotive clients here in Singapore. That company and then got into Web3 and started
Degenic. Prior to Aether, I was building a protocol as well. But I've since left the team to,
you know, go full time with Aether. The next question is people who are building AI related Web3
projects. What do you see them in common? Like, do they have a common background or have they worked
in big tech? In the crypto space, what I've mostly seen is there's kind of two subsets. One is the
consumer facing group, right? Which is they're building a lot in AI agents, right? Consumer
tools, wrappers around ChatGPT with token incentives. A lot of these tend to be younger guys from top
universities in the US, right? Building out of that new Silicon Valley culture. I think a lot of them
were crypto users or crypto natives because of the AI boom. They saw a lot of opportunity in merging the
two worlds. Then there's also the infrastructure side, which is a lot of really the deep tech guys,
the founder of 4G, who got into crypto and is now building AI protocol as well. A lot of these guys
that are building on the infrastructure side, right? Solving a lot of the incentive problems with like
open and closed source in AI that we see today. Very interesting demographic, I think, of crypto
builders in AI. Because we see there's a huge problem with GPU scarcity worldwide and companies
like Google, Meta, they're just racing to buy more and more NVIDIA GPUs. And it seems like people just
can't get enough GPUs. So tell us what is happening behind the scene. There's a common misconception
with the GPU scarcity problem, which is everyone thinks just we need more GPUs. I need more bullets.
That is pretty far from the truth. There are already a lot of data centers with a lot of existing,
whether it's high-end to mid-end to even low-end compute that's out there. The reason Amazon and
Google want to amass a lot of this is because they have really good control of the real bottleneck in the
GPUs, which is the software layer. In the GPU space, we have kind of three stacks that go from the
infrastructure as a service layer, the platform as a service layer, to the software as a service layer.
The software as a service layer is essentially what's closest to what users are used to with their
applications and SaaS tools that companies use. But between those tools, like everything that you see
on the internet and the actual GPU that's powering that compute, there's actually a layer in between,
which is the software layer, which encompasses all of the capabilities that you can do on these
computers, which include data cleansing, different types of rendering services, different types of cloud
hosting, server hosting, and things like that. And so when we look at the overall space, Amazon,
Google, they have really, really robust platform layers built either on top of them or with them.
And that's why it makes a lot of sense for them to amass GPUs. The Web3 approach has always been
give more utilization to these underutilized GPUs, right? We're aggregating GPUs from data centers,
from consumers to be able to be used by applications. But what's starkly lacking,
and what I like to talk a lot about with Aether is this platform layer, where Aether's team actually
has 10, 15 years of experience building out cloud infrastructure. And that's why we're able to,
we'll talk about this later on, but provide some of these cloud gaming, cloud phone, AI training use
cases to the biggest companies in the world. We're the only ones in deep end when crypto that are able
to do that today. And it's largely because there's a lack of software expertise that can actually use
this GPU. And so you can think about it as like, there's no point in buying a ton of bullets if
you don't have soldiers that know how to shoot, or you don't have the right guns to use them.
Can you tell me more about the software? You said there's a lack of software?
There's a lack of software expertise, right? And so right now, let's think about it this way.
One of the capabilities that Aether's built is the ability to do cloud gaming. So for example,
you could go Legends without having to download it. This gets more and more important in the gaming sector,
because as games, you know, get more AAA, they get more high quality, the file sizes start to become
ridiculous. You can't be downloading like a 500 gigabyte game onto your MacBook trying to play it.
In making that happen between the GPU that can actually power and host these games to the user
experiencing it and actually being able to play it, there's a lot of software in the middle that
actually needs to execute on this. Out rendering, right? Real-time instances, all of these different
platform, the hardware to actually be able to do the things that we want them to do to create these
capabilities. That's where Aether's team has a really, really strong advantage because of our
experiences and what we've been doing, you know, what the team's been doing for the past 10 to 15 years.
That's where there's a huge lag today, right? If you look at other deep end projects like Render or
Ionet, a lot of them are just being used for really simple AI inferences, very generic AI rendering use
cases. Hey, generate 50 photos for me. And you know, you can take like two weeks to do it as opposed to
cloud gaming where you need to use that powerful GPU to create an immediate render for the user to be
able to play it, like tens, millions of players to be able to play it within the same server.
You said the team has 10 to 15 years of experience. What were you doing before Aether then?
The team, not including me, but the team has a lot of past experience. If we look at from our CEO,
Dan, who was the ex-CEO of Riot Games China, all the way down to Kyle, our CTO with, you know, 10,
15 years building AI capabilities, different AI tech, even way before the AI boom. Some of our
software and development team that's built a lot of the cloud infrastructure across Asia and greater
Asia during the cloud boom from 2010 to 2020. Aether's team came together somewhere between 2018 to
2019 to really address the GPU shortage that was in gaming back then. And throughout that time,
we've built a ton of infrastructure to support things like cloud gaming, cloud phone. Up until
before the protocolization or till today, we've amassed over 30 million, closing in on 40 million
in annualized revenue. And that number is now, or it's projected to significantly spike because we
have so much demand for this compute from the AI sector. The team came together as people with
10 to 15 years of experience building out Tencent cloud, cloud gaming infrastructure,
live stream platforms, some of the largest live stream platforms in the world, with really this vision
of building software that works and allows high-end enterprise companies to be able to access
cheaper and underutilized compute. What is Aether or other Web3 projects' relationship with Web2
companies? Like, are they selling the compute power to them? And at what scale? A lot of Web3 projects,
what they're really doing is aggregating compute, underutilized compute from different data centers,
consumers, allowing that compute to be used by their clients. The problem, like I said, is because a lot
of these T-Bend projects lacked the software layer to do really interesting capabilities that actually
cost a ton of money. These clients that AWS and Google Cloud tend to serve, the revenue numbers are
actually very, very lacking. Some of these companies have public revenue reports, right? Some of them
don't. And this is where Aether kind of comes in and changes this. Aether's been building out this
infrastructure in a more centralized way in the past. And we have accrued 30, 40 million in ARR,
annual realized revenue. As we have shifted last month and this month towards the decentralized model
where anyone can plug into this network, anyone can provide compute to these clients, what you're
seeing is the existing compute providers are purchasing this amount of ATH to actually utilize
the network, right? And so that's where you can expect that there is going to be a lot of demand
or a lot of utilization of the token. And to make this more fair, most Web3 companies don't want to
show their revenue because if they did, everyone would realize that this project is grossly overvalued,
right? If you look at it from a revenue perspective, obviously revenue is not the only way to measure the
value of a company, but that's where Aether stands out. Aether actually has real demand and real
revenue. We've been servicing some of the largest game companies in the world, the largest telcos in the
world that serve hundreds of millions to billions of users. I'm not currently at liberty to disclose
the names of these companies, but because we have this revenue, what we're going to be releasing
between July and August is this thing that I've called proof of revenue. And what that means is
a lot of this revenue and a lot of this demand for compute is actually going to be publicly showcased
in our dashboard that's up and coming and also seen visibly on-chain as purchases of ATH to use
our protocol so that users can actually understand and see that there's real demand for this utility,
there's real demand for this network that can give them more confidence in the project.
I know you can't disclose the names, but can you describe who are these companies?
One of them is the game publisher of probably the most famous mobile game in the world.
It's a shooting game.
The other one is both the publisher and developer and owner of one of the largest games in the world,
multiplayer games in the world as well. So those are our cloud gaming use cases. On the cloud phone
side, we also have probably the largest telco in the world by user count. Again, I can't say their name,
but based on that description, users can probably go and speculate which company that is. There's only
a couple that I'm not getting that.
I assume it's in the US.
It is not.
What?
Yeah.
Well, it's not. Okay. Okay.
Well, I mean, telco's are based on country, right? So there's a couple geographies in the
world that have the most-
Yeah. Yeah. It's in Asia.
Maybe. Okay.
Why did the team create Aether?
Because you guys were serving Web2 companies or these team members were working for Web2 companies,
and I assume they're very successful. Why Aether?
The main problem that Aether has always addressed, whether it was in a traditional model or now in
the Web3 model, is the ability for the next generation of enterprise-grade GPU use cases,
right? Whether that's very high-end AI training with billions of parameters for model training,
or that's, like I said, cloud gaming for billions of users. Why we decided to go ahead and create a
distributed network? It just makes a ton of sense that you actually have a very, very large distributed
network, and they're all incentivized through one structure, right? And so where the token and the
protocol comes in is it's really solving an incentivization problem. Whereas if I have a
distributed network where I have H100s from all around the world, they plug into my network.
Whenever they don't have SLA that's ongoing, they can plug in and they can come in first a number
of time. You can think about them like all these enterprise-grade compute providers, they work on
very, very long-standing contracts. There's difficulty. Different regions get different contracts
at different times. And so if you have a single aggregation layer, it makes it a lot cleaner and a lot
simpler. And then when you bring in crypto economics, token economics to it, you're actually able to
provide these at a significantly lower cost as compared to doing it in a fully centralized way.
Because again, if I'm, let's say, a H100 in Malaysia, I can only service Malaysian clients.
I need to have a higher base fee or a higher base service fee to be able to make sure that I'm
profitable. But if I'm plugging into this network and I'm able to receive jobs from different places
and there's a software layer in between that's aggregating and distributing for me, I can already
lower my initial base costs. And then on top of that, we have like token stipends, tokens that
essentially act as very liquid credits to help bootstrap the system. That's where you can amass a ton
of high-end compute that can better serve our already existing long list of high-end enterprise-grade
clients. So you are already an established Web2 company that turned Web3, is that correct?
Yes. And we're now translating all of that revenue into buying ATH to use the protocol.
Well, that's so interesting. And you already have like an established customer base in Web2,
right?
Yeah, exactly.
Can you tell us more about your customers? Like when you switch from Web2 to Web3,
does that change your customer base?
Not at all. So what we've done to make this possible is we've created this thing that the
team likes to call a Web2 service layer. And so what that means is the experience for the customer,
the traditional customer of this enterprise, they can't pay in ATH, they can't pay in USDT,
they can only pay fiat currency. They can continue to have this existing service. And what we have in
the middle is essentially a software layer that allows these users to pay us, so not Aether Foundation,
but Aether Capital. They pay Aether in USD, and then there's a conversion into ATH,
and then that is directly used to purchase the compute from our network over each week to ensure
that there's consistent uptime and the GPU providers are still being rewarded the same amount.
So yeah, there's essentially no change to the revenue that we're realizing. There's no change
to the customer base. They're very satisfied with the existing uptime, the existing performance of
the GPUs. All we're doing is allowing all of that revenue to flow into our protocol and flow into our
decentralized network to make it even more bullish during the bootstrap period.
That's what I love to hear, like a real use and like existing revenue stream. You do have four
business units, right? Cloud gaming, Cloud Phone, AI training, and edge compute. What are the
differences? So cloud gaming, like I mentioned, is imagine you can play any game without needing to
download it, right? Because the game is hosted on a server. Right now, there's two major use cases.
One is AAA games that are extremely big in file size to allow users to experience it before download.
The second is with even smaller to medium games, there's actually a huge barrier of user acquisition
when you're trying to convince the user to sign up and download the game. And so what we do for
these companies is, hey, here's a link. It allows you to play a 15-minute demo of the game. It
automatically creates an account for you. If you play the game and you like it, you have way more
incentive to then download the game and sign up, right? And so we work with a lot of these smaller
to medium gaming companies to offer this. It's very cheap if you're only allowing the user to play for,
let's say, 10, 15 minutes of a demo. And it significantly lowers the barrier of entry for the
user to have the first gaming experience. With Cloud Phone, Cloud Phone is actually very, very interesting.
What it is, is essentially hosting the entire hardware capability of your phone on a cloud. And so what that means is
with a link, let's say you had like a $50 chip. As long as it has access to the internet and has a
screen, you could plug into the cloud and you could have an iPhone, right? You could be using an iPhone
and have the same capabilities as an iPhone or even, you know, the highest end mobile phone out there
just through that cloud instance. And so we see a huge demand for this in Asia right now, right?
Because a lot of users there, maybe they don't want to spend $1,000 on an iPhone, but what they can do
is, you know, buy a $200 phone and then pay $10 a month for a subscription service that essentially
creates these Cloud Phone instances for them and allows them to have the experience of using an iPhone
iPhone without needing to buy an iPhone. AI training is something that everyone is familiar with.
We're special compared to other Deepin projects, just like I mentioned, because we have by far the
most number of high-end GPUs, right? We have over 4,000 H100s, all the H100s, probably a hundred X of
all the H100s in the rest of Deepin or crypto combined, apart from IO, which has a thousand H100s listed on
their platform, but those are all our H100s as well. And so when you have this critical mass of high-end
compute, what you're essentially able to do is provide close to centralized level services for AI
training, right? And so we have companies running 750 million parameter models that are being trained
on our cloud infrastructure, which is really awesome. And then finally, edge compute. Edge compute,
what it's really talking about is low-latency inference for AI. And so what that means is
bringing the inference closer to you. And so, for example, let's say you're using ChatGPT,
running an instance to ask it a question. If the servers are hosted far away from you,
it takes longer for the instance to run, right? Or for that inference to happen. And so having these
edge computing devices distributed around the world allows the inference to happen closer to the
user, meaning it can happen a lot faster. With text generation, it's not a big problem. But then
when you go to video generation, AI agents, right, we see a huge demand for companies or networks with
edge compute capabilities. And so that's why our first partner, Aether Edge, they've built these
devices in partnership with Qualcomm that has this chip that allows for over 100 different models or
types of inferences to be run on it. And we're using that to service our existing clients.
That just triggered three questions. The first is on CloudPhone. I did not know that was happening in
Asia. Can you tell me more about CloudPhone? So people buy like a cheaper version, and then they
plug it into their computer? So they're not plugging into their computer. How we've been doing it so far
is directly in partnership with the Telco. So remember, I mentioned we have partnerships with
the largest Telco in the world by user base. And the service they offer is essentially this. You can buy
any phone you want from the Telco, right? Buy a SIM card. When you connect to that Telco's internet
service, there's an option that's, you know, on top of your subscription. Let's say you're paying like
$15 a month for your phone bill. You pay an additional $10. And what that Telco does is it allows you to plug
into this cloud where it's hosting the rest of the phone software for you. What it is, is like you
would download an app and then it creates a new instance on your chip that allows you to use like
a second phone that's in your phone. I see. Yeah. Or moving that to the cloud. And so what that means
is you can have your mobile phone today, whatever it is, and you can plug it into it. You pay this $10
subscription, it plugs into the Telco's network. And that cloud infrastructure basically gives your
phone way more capability. So again, like for example, you can have an iPhone running on a $200 phone.
The phone that you have is not an iPhone, right? The hardware isn't an iPhone, but it has the
capabilities of an iPhone. That's the software level is hosted on the cloud for you.
So it'll look like an iOS system. Yeah, exactly. And it could do all the things that an iOS system
can do. Traditionally, like your $200 phone wouldn't be able to do. Why would Apple allow
that? Yeah. So that's, that's a different question entirely. What we're mostly using it for right now
is essentially like very specific services that allow you to, for example, with a single phone,
right? You could spin up like five different accounts, right? Let's say you wanted to have
five different accounts that act as five different personas, right? Or you wanted to have separate
instances for, let's say your WeChat, your Alipay, right? You have one instance that's mainly for
your bank account. And then one instance that's mainly for gaming, for example, right? Your phone
is, you know, it's cheaper. So it doesn't really have the bandwidth to handle all these things at the
same time. You can spin up separate instances for that and do them separately, and it doesn't overload
your phone. Oh, okay. That makes a lot more sense. We see Crypto Project addressing this
GPU scarcity problem by selling nodes, right? So basically allows users to provide their own GPU,
compute power for these AI gaming movie companies to use. And from these companies' perspective,
though, they want reliable supply. So for example, an AI startup or gaming company would need GPU that
are operational 24-7. But my question is, when the GPUs are controlled by retail users,
isn't it difficult to prevent issues like power cuts or shortages?
That is one of the reasons why Aether is probably the only Deepin project that can truly actually
service these enterprise-grade customers. Let's say you're using my MacBook, right? To render
these 50 images. Rendering images is okay if you have no timeline for it, right? Let's say I'm okay
with these 50 images being rendered in two weeks. You don't care if I'm using my laptop to play
Teamfight Tactics or watch Netflix half the time. But in true Web2 enterprises, if you're servicing,
like I said, these billions of users for cloud gaming or for, you know, cloud phone instances,
network uptime is really, really important, right? And in the Web2 traditional GPU world,
we have these things called SLAs, which basically mean as a compute provider, I guarantee you a
certain like 99% uptime or 95% uptime. And I guarantee you that there's commitment of the
bandwidth, right? Of this machine to be working on yours. And that's why Aether is currently allowing
our onboarding compute providers based on a whitelist segmentation, right? Or through a whitelist
function. We do allow, and we will allow, you know, any and every user to be able to come in and
contribute to the network. But the types of jobs you might receive or you might be eligible for are very
different. If you're a consumer that, again, is like plugging in your MacBook to the network,
you might, you will still be eligible for these smaller jobs and, you know, smaller projects or
smaller compute jobs if the user doesn't have a really high SLA or have a really big demand for
uptime. But for the large enterprises that we're serving, right? If a compute provider wants to come
in, they want to provide a hundred H100s, right? Like tens, hundreds of million dollars of compute,
then there is a requirement within the network that they guarantee the uptime. Otherwise,
they'll get slashed and then we'll pick another compute provider or another, you know,
really high-end enterprise-grade GPU to do the job for them.
If I have a MacBook, for example, what type of job can my GPU do?
Some level of AI inference, right? So for example, running an instance of chat GPT to some level of
rendering. If you're talking about game rendering, you could probably host a game for like five to
10 players. They do run in the background, but they're used when you're using the laptop,
right? So when a lot of these deep end projects talk about underutilized GPU, what they're really
talking about is, okay, you're having lunch or you're sleeping, right? Your computer is on,
not doing anything. Your GPU is not being used. It's in the background.
The second question is on IO.net. You said a hundred of their GPUs are yours.
IO.net right now, I think they have about 1,500 H100s on their system. A thousand of them are ours.
A thousand. Okay. Why are you sharing your GPUs with IO.net? So it sounds like you guys are not
competitors. You guys are more like partners.
What you can think about Aether's focus as is really serving these enterprise clients, right?
High-end enterprise grade gaming AI use cases. And to do that, we need to have compute providers that
have a robust stock, right? You can think about a robust bandwidth of these H100 machines, right?
But it doesn't mean these H100 machines are always in use. And so, whereas IO is really a compute
orchestration layer, right? And so what we're doing is we're listing these devices on IO.net. And so if
you're a compute provider and you wanted to gain access to a H100, you can gain access to our H100s,
right from our network directly through IO.net's interface. If these H100s are being taken up and
being used for other purposes, then you wouldn't be able to rent them on IO.net server anymore.
Now, so you can think of it as like, we have a bunch of seats on airplanes and we don't really
care if it's being bought from trip.com or it's from like Click or it's being bought from Expedia.
It's just another place where we can list these devices.
Now, here's a question. How would you describe Aether to, let's say, your grandparents?
That's something I think about every day. Imagine right now, there's a huge demand for GPUs.
All the people with these really high-end GPUs, they can come in, they can plug in,
they can provide compute to these gaming companies, these telco companies, these AI companies at very,
very high guarantees at enterprise grade that needs to fit their needs. And we do it because
we have really, really advanced software.
So who do you think your competitors are?
Honestly, the way I see Deepin today is that it's almost too early for there to be a competitive
scene. Every single Deepin project today does something very, very unique. Obviously,
within Deepin, we're all competing for mindshare and we're all competing for user recognition.
But what we do at a business level is very, very different. Ionet acts as a very
high-level orchestration layer. Render is very much so for consumer compute to plug in and do
render jobs. You have projects like Grass, which is using essentially your computer's bandwidth.
And for us, we're really, really focused on this enterprise grade gaming and AI use cases.
And so in the business model, there's virtually no competition in the Web3 space. But again,
all of us are Deepin projects. When retail looks for which Deepin project to bet on,
they're looking at all of us equally. So that's usually how I think about the problem.
So if users look at you equally, then what sets you apart?
I think what really sets us apart is the fact that we're able to generate and accrue real revenue.
One, because of the actually massive amount of high-end enterprise-grade compute and compute
machines we have. And then two is, again, the actual software layer that we built that's able
to enable these use cases. Very few companies in the world that can actually provide cloud gaming
to hundreds of millions of users at the same time. In Web2 or Web3, I think there's maybe a total
of 10 to 20 companies that can do it. In Web3, there's definitely only one, and it's either.
Because we have these software capabilities and this huge amount of high-end compute,
that means we're actually able to service real enterprise clients. That means we actually have
real contracts. We have projected almost 250 million ARR in the next work year.
And based on our protocol design, in order for this ARR to be converted to compute,
it first has to be converted to ATH. And I think that's a very, very standout point.
There is just a lot of natural demand for the token, even before the token was released,
because of the way we built out the ecosystem. And that's definitely a standout point,
not just in Deepin, but for any crypto company. I think it's hard for any crypto company to say
that they have guaranteed buy, like buying or guaranteed demand for the utility of the token.
So when I hear your revenue, I'm like, wow, that sounds like a lot. But how does that number
compare to other Deepin projects? It's not going to sound great when I say it,
but we have more monthly revenue than the lifetime revenue of all other Deepin projects combined,
based on whatever information is public today.
That's insane. What are some exciting projects that you're working on? I heard there's A-Phone,
and there is Impossible Finance. Can you tell us more about that?
So A-Phone is one of the projects within our ecosystem. It's not built by Aether ourselves.
It's a Web3 team that looked at our CloudFone capabilities and were like, hey,
we want to build a Web3 version of this. We also have, like I said, Aether Edge,
which is a manufacturing company that came in and said, look, hey, you know,
we have tons of experience in building hardware. We have this partnership with Qualcomm.
We want to build these edge mining devices to power your edge computing use cases.
These smaller ecosystem projects or even larger ecosystem projects like Rivals,
like Carve and Web3 that are building and gaming and AI that are plugging in and directly using our
compute. And so that's what our ecosystem looks like. With Impossible Finance, we have a very,
very close relationship with them. We're working with them to incubate more projects. And I'm
actively overseeing that as I build out the Aether Grants program, the Aether EcoFund,
to be able to better support projects that want to build on top of our compute and build on top of
our ecosystem. And on top of that, we also have a ton more partnerships on the more DeFi native side.
We just announced one with SoFan where users can stake A-T-H and then they can go and restake it with
SoFan to be able to get more rewards on more tokens. And a lot of our partners that do use our
compute, they actually do end up providing additional tokens somewhere between 0.5 to 2%
of their FDB to actually reward our users, whether that's the checker note holders or that's the
stakers that are securing the network for us. That's essentially all that we're cooking. There's a
lot. To summarize it, what's up and coming really is more partnerships, more clients, more revenue,
and also more DeFi native use cases. And finally, governance, which I'm hoping to launch in about
two to three months.
Exciting. Any more alphas you can share with us for the viewers today?
We're going to be releasing publicly a lot more on information about the partnership with Ionet.
KreeTG both announced a $50 million token swap. And that token swap is meant to reward users within
our mutual ecosystems.
See, before this interview, I thought you and Ionet are competitors, but now you guys are just
like best friends working together.
I think what we both recognize is that without each other, it's very hard usually for one project to
build a sector of crypto by itself. If you look at the L2 space, Arbitrum, Optimism,
Base, they all came together. They're all slightly different, but they work together to build out the
entire segment of that industry. And I think we both recognize that without each other, it's very hard
for us to stand alone and say like, hey, Deepin matters or Deepin is a real thing if there's only
one project working on it. And so we love to see them win and I hope they feel the same.
I checked your tokenomics and it says checkers and compute providers will get half of the total
token allocation. Can you tell us more about that?
So how we've broken it down is, like I said, Aether was built as a protocol to bootstrap a network that
actually makes sense. The checkers, you can think of them as server management software, right? And
so they make sure that all the compute providers are actually honest and providing compute and doing
the jobs like they said that would, similar to how traditional server management software would
maintain the SLAs. Then we have the actual compute providers that are plugging in, you know,
their H100s, high-end GPUs, T4s, M4s into our network and doing the compute jobs. And then we have
Edge Compute with Aether Edge recently to start releasing these devices to the public where users can
essentially run these machines at home and support these AI inference use cases.
If I'm interested now, how can I participate?
Because the Aether licenses are not transferable for the first year, the best way for someone that's
new to the Aether ecosystem to participate is one, either by getting yourself an Aether Edge device or
two, participating in our staking pools. So we have two staking pools, Aether Gaming as well as Aether AI.
They all have native ATH rewards for staking your tokens, but you also get additional tokens from our
partners depending on which pool you staked in. So if you staked in the gaming pool, gaming projects that use
our compute would then add tokens to the submission pool. If you staked into the AI pool, then AI
projects that use our compute or partner with us would then add tokens to this pool instead.
What is a staked token for?
So what the staked token really is allowing for better crypto economic security of the network.
It's not validator staking or proof of stake like Ethereum is because we're not an L1 blockchain.
What staking does is it essentially secures the network from an economic standpoint. For the compute
providers and also the edge devices, they also stake. They stake a certain amount so that if they're
acting maliciously or trying to manipulate the rewards, then there's a locked pool of tokens there to punish them.
For users that aren't compute providers or don't have an edge device, the staking is essentially a way to show
commitment and belief to the long-term revenue and also the long-term build of Aether.
Now we want to talk about D-PIN because D-PIN, this term was created by Mazzari in late 2022, so pretty late.
And this term started gaining attention only late last year. I remember when it first came out, many
people questioned this narrative because this concept has been around for a while. If it's been around for a
while, why has it only become popular now? What has changed?
We always talk about Render as the first D-PIN, right? And it's really interesting because they
came out and did this before D-PIN was a thing. They were like, hey, why don't we just use crypto
to incentivize underutilized GPUs to do compute jobs, right? The problem of compute being underutilized
has existed for a really, really long time. I think the shifting point is definitely in AI. In the past,
there wasn't really a GPU shortage, so no one really cared if there was a ton of underutilized
compute. But now with the boom of AI, there's huge demand for compute. And when you do have a GPU
shortage, right, it's like when you run out of money, suddenly remember you have coins like that
you left around. Very simple concept. But for the entire kind of AI and tech industry, it's what
they're starting to realize. And that's why there's more and more emphasis on, hey, deep and make
sense. But again, I think there's still a very, very big gap here where you see a huge demand for
compute. But for the underutilized compute or for spare compute to actually be able to be used for
what the demand needs, there's a huge gap in the software layer between, you know, the platform as a
service and the software as a service layers.
Some of the so-called AI coins or AI products may not actually be AI, but just simply an AI meme coin.
What are some problems you see in the AI and Deepin sector in Web3 right now?
But the biggest problem is like between AI and Deepin, the story makes a lot of sense. Again,
AI needs a ton of compute. There's a ton of underutilized compute. Why don't we just bootstrap
it using crypto or using a token? And then we can bridge that gap. But again, the real gap there is,
can this underutilized compute actually do what the AI needs to do? And in time, or whether it can
actually train that, you know, really, really large model, or it can really render those pictures,
the compute that's being provided needs to have the right amount of uptime, the right amount of
server management, the right type of server management software, and the right software in
between to actually have it do the right work. And so that's kind of where the gap is today. And I
think if users are really looking at which projects to believe in, the numbers actually show very
obviously from revenue. So two things. One is revenue, and then two is utilization rate. There are
Deepin projects that have millions of underutilized compute plugged into them. But even after you plug into
the network, it's still underutilized. And it's not underutilized because there's no demand for this type of
compute. It's underutilized because there's a gap in the software layer. The AI companies, the startups,
they want cheaper compute, but they can't use the ones that are being provided by a lot of Deepin
projects because there's not enough uptime, there's not enough bandwidth, there's not enough management
of these compute devices that are being plugged in. We're probably the only Deepin project in this
space that's actually able to guarantee these things, whether it's for enterprises or for medium-sized
startups. And that's why I talk about revenue, right? It shows in the revenue. We have this revenue
because we're actually able to service this demand. Earlier, I think you touched on the software layer,
why you guys are the only one that can achieve this, right? Can you elaborate more and tell us
more about this gap you were talking about? Ather actually has over 100 engineers around the world
working on this platform as a service layer, the compute that's provided by the compute providers
and the applications that are actually using the compute. It is this way because each application
has its own specific needs. A gaming company can say, hey, I need compute. What does it need to
compute for, right? Is it running a single instance on the cloud for a game? Is it doing some AI
generation within the game? Each of these instances require the compute to be utilized and used in a
different way. And that's what the software in between does. It's telling the computer what it
actually needs to do. And for this to be able to service large companies, Fortune 500s, enterprise
grade, billion dollar revenue companies beyond bandwidth and uptime, the feature set actually
needs to be very, very complete before they can use it. And so that's something that we're
consistently scaling the team to be able to do and growing the team to better service more and more
companies. We actually have hundreds of companies on our waitlist right now that say, hey,
I want access to your compute, but I need it to come with this feature set. And so we're building
out those feature sets more and more to onboard more revenue and more customers every day.
So you have better engineers and better software layer than other people?
We have a more experienced engineering team. And the thing is, we actually have this commitment
to building it. I think there's a lot of deep end projects that bootstrap the compute,
they issue the tokens to the compute providers, and then they don't do the actual hard part,
right? Which is connecting the compute to the demand. The reason we want to have proof of revenue,
the reason that we're showcasing all of this publicly is because we want to make this public
statement, right? Make this public commitment to the fact that we're actually here to
build this thing after the token is launched and actually make sure that the demand is actually
serviced by our compute providers.
This is me asking you your personal opinion. So I want to know what your due diligence process
look like in case you want to invest in like a deep end project. How do you spot a real winner?
I think it's pretty similar to due diligence for any crypto project, right? It's looking into the
background of the team and it's looking at over time. And I think especially for deep end,
this is true. It's do they actually do what they say they do? Because again,
bootstrapping compute is the easy part, right? Actually servicing the demand is the
hard part for them to actually find customers and then build the software so that these customers
can use your compute is, you know, the single defining factor of whether or not this project
or this company can actually exist five years from now.
We talk on the channel that for this crypto bull run to happen, a few conditions must align.
Bitcoin having QE environment, traditional finance fund getting into crypto and new narrative.
So speaking of new narrative, do you believe that Deepin is the new narrative we're waiting for?
The one weakness that Deepin has from a narrative perspective is that it's hard for users to really
interface with them. It's different from DeFi. It's different from NFTs that has fueled our last
bull runs where users can come in and immediately do something. Where it gets really interesting or
where the Deepin narrative needs to really take off is there needs to be projects that actually come
out and say like, like an AI agent project that says, hey, we're built on top of this Deepin.
You're using, you know, you can interact with this AI agent or this AI assistant because of this Deepin.
And it's much cheaper because of this Deepin. It's going to really feel the narrative for Deepin.
That's why I'm so excited about us announcing our eco grants program and our eco fund program.
And yeah, working on it every day to make it go to market as soon as possible.
A lot of experts are saying that one reason we're not seeing a crazy bull run so far is because
traditional finance markets attention is all on AI, like AI related stocks. You see Nvidia going up,
TSMC has hit all time high and it's just attracting a lot of investors from institutional wise and retail
investors. Do you think this is true? I don't think that there is a shortage of demand for
larger funds and tradfire companies to want to partake in crypto, but there is a compliance,
right? Or legislation barrier there. If compliance can move forward for crypto, I don't think there's
any shortage of demand from tradfire companies to want exposure to our space. It's really down to a
compliance issue. Experts are saying there might be a stock market downturn, right? And on the other hand,
we are still waiting for this crypto bull market to really boom. Do you think deep end price will
follow this AI related stock or crypto market? Because it's kind of in the middle.
Not financial advice to anyone. What I think is it follows both and we've seen it with render
throughout the cycle. Render is one of the better performing tokens throughout this like semi bull
market that we've had. And a lot of it is driven by the speculation around Nvidia. I don't think that's
going to change from a retail perspective. A lot of these deep end projects are still more
affected by general crypto sentiment than it is by the AI sentiment. Or well, the non-hardware related
tech stocks is they are still backed very, very strongly by something that's more real, which is
revenue, right? Which is demand as compared to what a lot of tech stocks are backed by, which is user
count. It's purely speculation, right? There's very little real value that's driving a lot of this.
And so it's significantly less sustainable. And that's why I will come back now and show Aether,
not financial advice. But even in the deepest of bear markets, if there's a real demand,
there's real revenue. And especially for us, because of the way the protocol is designed,
this real revenue is directly again converted into buy pressure because the users need the
ATH token to access the compute. That changes how resistant you are, or it changes the way that your
token might play out in market conditions. Help me visualize how big this potential size of D-PIN
sector is going to be. If we look at our total addressable marketing growth today, AI training,
7.1 billion. Cloud gaming, 1.9 billion. Cloud phone, 22 billion. Edge compute, 2 billion. Based on growth
projections, in five years, the lower bound of just the market that our business unit addresses and
not all of D-PIN is 33 billion. And the upper bound is 76 billion. And that's in real actualized
revenue, right? That's not taking into account the multiples that you see in the crypto market.
It could potentially be massive. Again, not financial advice.
Well, that was insightful. I love that. Anything else you want to add?
Something I will end off with is a lot of projects see the token launch or TGE as the beginning
of the end. Sorry, 12 June was when we TGE'd. We haven't even shown more than 10% of what we really
have and what we've really been working on the last four to five years. Protocolization of the real
businesses since 2021. But there's a lot that's ongoing. And if you look at our tokenomics,
emissions are planned for four years, five years, 10 years. We want to be a project that's here to
stay. We believe we can do it because we have real revenue. And it's not targeted at driving
short-term speculation. It's built towards incentivizing long-term value and long-term participation.
Thank you, Jayden. That was very insightful. And I honestly learned so much from you.
Yeah. Thank you so much for having me. It was an absolute pleasure.
Thank you so much for having me. It was an absolute pleasure.